A Guide to the John Nicolay Papers, 1792-1895
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
John Nicolay Papers, 1792-1985
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Ms87-027
1.4 cubic feet, 3 boxes, 45 folders, cassette tapes
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open to research.
Biographical/Historical Information
John Nicolay was a former Blacksburg, Virginia, resident and historian. The collection consists of papers Nicolay has used for his research on the history of Montgomery County, Virginia. The topics he researched included in the collection are poverty in Montgomery County, blacks, local churches, and the Edie Family of Christiansburg, Virginia.
Scope and Content Information
The types of materials in the collection include oral history tapes, slides, original documents and historical photographs of the area by Earl Palmer. In addition, there is material from Moutainside Magazine, edited by Nicolay from 1983 to 1984, such as writings by Beverly Brinlee, Jess Carr, Fred Waage, and William White.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged according to subject matter.
Contents List
- Poverty on Montgomery County, Virginia: Documents 1790-1819 (Box-folder 1-1)
- Poverty in Montgomery County, Virginia: Reports of Overseers of the Poor 1799-1859 (Box-folder 1-2)
- Poverty in Montgomery County, Virginia: Tithables 1805-1813 (Box-folder 1-3)
- Poverty in Montgomery County, Virginia: Settlements 1805-1823 (Box-folder 1-4)
- Poverty in Montgomery County, Virginia: Documents 1820-1865 (Box-folder 1-5)
- Poverty in Montgomery County, Virginia: Documents 1866-1880 (Box-folder 1-6)
- Poverty in Montgomery County, Virginia: Miscellaneous, letters, reciepts, notes 1878 (Box-folder 1-7)
- Poverty in Montgomery County, Virginia: Documents 1901-1918 (Box-folder 1-8)
- Poverty in Montgomery County, Virginia: Miscellaneous 1904 (Box-folder 1-9)
- Montgomery County [VA] Order Book 1792-1793 (Box-folder 1-10)
- Montgomery County [VA] History 1880-1890 (Box-folder 1-11)
- Copies of Historical Documents Concerning the History of Montgomery County, VA (Box-folder 1-12)
- Christiansburg Institute [I] (Box-folder 1-13)
- Christiansburg Institute [II] (Box-folder 1-14)
- Free Black registers for Montgomery County, VA 1806-1818 (Box-folder 1-15)
- Gentry Bigamy Case, Montgomery County, VA 1818-1827 (Box-folder 1-16)
- Warrants against Granville Page, Montgomery County, VA 1844-1858 (Box-folder 1-17)
- Summons in Case of "the Commonwealth of Virginia and Gilbert, a Slave...," Montgomery County, VA 1850 (Box-folder 1-18)
- Criminal Complaint for Assault, Montgomery County, VA 1872 (Box-folder 1-19)
- Criminal Complaint for Theft, Montgomery County, VA 1889 (Box-folder 1-20)
- Material about Charles Edie 1872-1930 (Box-folder 1-21)
- The Honorable Murder of Charlie Edie 1857-1983 (Box-folder 1-22)
- Tax Bond, Montgomery County, VA 1782 (Box-folder 1-23)
- Bills to Montgomery County, VA, for Services Rendered 1841-1846 (Box-folder 1-24)
- Letter, Chrishan to Hemings 1875 (Box-folder 1-25)
- "Devil's Den" and "Devil's Armchair" Landmarks in Montgomery County, VA, n.d. 1973 (Box-folder 1-26)
- Churches, Montgomery County, VA, n.d. (Box-folder 1-27)
- "Draper's Meadow and Smithfield," 1980 (Box-folder 1-28)
- Shufflebarger[?] Cabin 1973 (Box-folder 1-29)
- Allen Cabin on Brush Mountain, Montgomery County, VA, n.d. (Box-folder 1-30)
- Kent Papers 1812-1982 (Box-folder 1-31)
- Lewis Miller 1957 (Box-folder 1-32)
- "George Hancock, Sr., of Fortheringhay," 1972 (Box-folder 1-33)
- Craig Cemetary 1982 (Box-folder 1-34)
- "Pearisburg Gazette," 1870 (Box-folder 1-35)
- Lynching in Smyth County, VA 1889 (Box-folder 1-36)
- Snowville, Pulaski County, VA 1937 (Box-folder 1-37)
- Wake Forest, VA: Documents 1982-1983 (Box-folder 1-38)
- Wake Forest, VA: Images, n.d. (Box-folder 1-39)
- "Entitled: Free Papers in Appalachia," 1978-1980 (Box-folder 1-40)
- Mountainside Magazine 1981-1983 (Box-folder 2-1)
- "West of the Blue Ridge," n.d. (Box-folder 2-2)
- Photographs by Earl Palmer of the Montgomery County and Blue Ridge, Scenes of Past and Present, n.d. (Box-folder 2-3)
- Photos of Production Cast of "Charlie Brown," 1983 (Box-folder 2-4)
- Images, Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box-folder 2-5)
- Cassette Tapes 1982-1983, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Interviewee: Bannister, Frank July 23, 1982
  - Interviewee: S.B. January 27, 1983, n.d., Two cassette tapes
  - Interviewee: Johnson, Sonny July 15, 1982, n.d., Two cassette tapes
  - Interviewee: New River Symposium April 16, 1983
  - Interviewee: Page, Clarence July 6, 1982, June 15, 1982, Three cassette tapes
  - Interviewee: Sherman, Oscar July 8, 1982